（ナレーション）＜西暦２１９９年＞
＜地球は
ガミラスとの戦いに敗れ→
滅びゆこうとしていた＞
＜人類滅亡まで　あと１年＞
＜宇宙戦艦ヤマトは
地球を再生させる→
コスモリバースシステムを
受け取るため→
１６万８０００光年のかなた
イスカンダルへと旅立った＞
＜太陽系を離れ
大マゼランへと急ぐヤマト＞
＜　その行く手には　さまざまな
試練が待ち受けていた＞
（島）ヤマトの現在位置は　ここ。→
This is the Yamato's current location.
そして　次のワープで
ヤマトは　実質的に→
And our next warp will take us out of the galaxy.
そして　次のワープで
ヤマトは　実質的に→
銀河系を離脱します。
銀河外縁部と
大マゼランの距離は→
41 kiloparsecs separate our galaxy and the Large Magellanic Cloud.
およそ４１キロパーセク。→
つまり　この先には
いまだ　１３万光年という→
In other words, we still have 130,000 light years of unknown space ahead.
つまり　この先には
いまだ　１３万光年という→
未知の空間が
待ち受けているわけです。
（沖田十三）うむ。
（真田）銀河系を突破すれば→
Once we're beyond the Milky Way, our enemy will stop pursuing us so closely.
敵の追撃も少なくなるでしょう。
（徳川）どういうことかね？
（真田）それは…。
Why do you say that?
That's...
（新見）
文明を発祥させる条件→
When you consider the conditions required for civilization...
That is, the number of available systems,
つまり　恒星系の数を考えると
ガミラス星は→
it's likely the Garmillas System exists within our own galaxy.
銀河系内に存在すると考えるのが
自然だからです。
（南部）言われてみれば　そうだよ。
Come to think of it, you're right.
（古代進）なんにしても
ガミラスとの遭遇率が→
Either way, it'll be good to have the Garmillans off our backs for a while.
低くなるのは助かるなぁ。
You're so relaxed... You amaze me.
お前は　のんきだな。
まったく　あきれるよ。
（森雪）あっ。
どういう意味だ？
What do you mean?
（森雪）あっ。
どういう意味だ？
I'm saying that you shouldn't be taking it so easy.
（島）緊張感が欠けていると
言ってるんだ。
ちょっと待てよ。　俺のどこが
緊張感がないっていうんだ？
Wait a second.
What makes you think I'm taking it easy?
つまらない理想主義も
いいかげんにしろって話さ。
You're being stupidly idealistic.
Are you talking about Melda?
メルダの件を言っているのか？
（島）所詮　彼女は　ガミラス人だ！
She's a Garmillan!
それとこれとは　話が違うだろ！
That has nothing to do with this.
じゃあ　お前は
メルダの言った話を信じるんだな？
So you believe what she said, don't you? That we fired first!
俺たちが　先に
戦争を仕掛けたって言うんだな!?
いつ　俺が　そんなことを言った！
言ってるも同じだ！
When did I say that?
Well, you basically said so!
（南部）まあまあ　君たち…。
（島・古代）お前は黙ってろ！
Calm down, guys.
You shut up!
Be quiet, you fools!
バカ者!!
（２人）うっ！　あぁ…。
（佐渡）
血圧が　ちょっと高いようですな。
Your blood pressure's a little high.
I'll keep an eye out.
面倒をかける。
（佐渡）聞きましたよ。→
I heard about it.
若い連中は
頭に　血が上りやすい。→
The young ones lose their tempers easily.
You have to control yourself, too.
あんたも　無理はいかんよ。
ふふっ。　かなわんな　先生には。
You always know what I'm thinking.
まったく　あのクソおやじめ。
Curse that old man...
"You lack the self-awareness required of an officer."
「お前たちには
士官としての自覚がない！」→
This is what they do to punish elementary school children.
って…
これじゃ　小学生の罰当番だって。
Let's finish this up and hit the next one.
おい
早く　ここ終わらして　次行こうぜ。
（島）こっちは終わった。
I'm done.
They're offering a limited-time Milky Way lunch in the cafeteria. Want to try it?
今　食堂で　期間限定
天の川ランチってのをやっててさ→
今度　食いに行かないか？
ったく…。
Honestly...
（徳川）
そうか…　島に　あの話をしたのか。
I see. So you told Shima.
（山崎）ええ。
Yes.
（徳川）あいつ
それで　イラついとったのか。→
Then that's what had him so upset.
Do you regret it?
後悔しとるのか？
（山崎）いえ。
No, he was Captain Daigo Shima's son. He'll accept the truth.
彼は
あの島大吾一佐のご子息です。
事実を
正面から受け止めてくれる→
That is what I believe.
そう　自分は信じています。
You really think so? People in high positions can be surprisingly fragile.
≪（薮）そうかな～？
ん？
（薮）エリートって
意外と　もろいもんですよ。→
じゃあ　お先に上がります。
I'll be off, then.
そう…。
I see.
ありがと　助かったわ。
Thank you. It's a big help.
You're welcome. Please excuse me.
（薮）はい！　失礼します。
≪シューン　シューン（ドアの音）
お待ちください。
（セレステラ）ん？
Please wait.
His Lordship is using the hot-line right now.
総統は　ただいま
ホットラインを　ご使用中です。
（セレステラ）ホットライン？
おどきなさい。
The hot-line?
Out of the way.
But...
しかし…。
（セレステラ）おどきなさい！
Out of the way!
（デスラー）ははははっ。
それは　私の誤解だったようだ。→
It seems I misunderstood.
I thought you'd gone back to your old tricks out of pity for them.
私は　てっきり
君が　彼らを哀れんで→
また　悪い癖を出してしまったかと
思ってね。→
You are my country's heart and soul. Naturally, I'm worried.
君は　我が国の心の支えだ。
心配するのは当たり前のことだよ。
宇宙の平安は→
Peace in the universe is only possible because of our friendship.
我々の友好あってのこと。→
Isn't that right?
≪そうだろう？
次は
じかに会って　語らいたいものだ。
Next I'd like to speak to you in person. We'll talk again some other time.
では　改めて。
なんだね？　二人そろって。
What brings you two here?
ドメル中将への叙勲式の用意が
整いました。
Preparations for Senior General Domel's medal ceremony have been completed.
分かった。　ギムレー　君の方は？
Very well. What about you, Gimleh?
（ギムレー）秘密警察の内偵で　新たに→
I've come to report the secret police's latest findings.
判明したことを
お知らせに参りました。
Regarding the rogue elements within the empire.
国内の不穏分子についてです。
I shall leave this to you. Handle it in any way you wish.
（デスラー）君に任せるよ。
手段は　問わずともよい。
I will take care of it.
手際よく処理いたします。
More importantly...
（デスラー）そんなことよりも…。
（セレステラ）例のテロン人の艦ですね？
That is the Terron ship, yes?
Where are they heading?
彼らは
どこを目指しているのか→
What is the end of their journey?
どこに向かって
旅を続けているのか→
それが　どうやら分かったよ。
It appears we've found out.
ふっ。
（一同）ガーレ・ドメル！
ガーレ・ドメル！→
Ghale Domel!
ガーレ・ドメル！
ガーレ・ドメル！→
Ghale Domel! Ghale Domel!
ガーレ・ドメル！　ガーレ・ドメル！
（ドメル）止めろ。
Stop the car.
General!
我らが将軍。
ありがとう。
（一同）ガーレ・ドメル！→
Thank you.
Ghale Domel! Ghale Domel!
ガーレ・ドメル！　ガーレ・ドメル！
（拍手）
ガーレ・フュゼロン！
Ghale Phuzeron!
私が　なぜ
君を　前線から召還したのか→
You're perhaps wondering why I've recalled you from the front lines.
計り兼ねている顔だな。
小マゼラン辺境は→
The Small Magellanic Cloud is the lynchpin of our defenses.
帝国防衛の要です。
指揮官の不在は→
The absence of a commanding officer aids the enemy.
敵を利することに
なります。
実は　銀河方面で
ちょっとした問題が起きてね。
There has been a problem within the Milky Way Theatre.
（ドメル）うわさは耳にしました。
我々の包囲網を突破している→
I've heard the rumors. A Terron ship broke through our dragnet.
テロンの宇宙船ですね。→
あのシュルツも
それで戦死したとか。
And Schultz fell in battle against them?
I would like for you to take care of this barbarian ship.
その野蛮人の艦を
君に討伐してきてもらいたいのだ。
行ってくれるかね？
Will you go?
（拍手）
If that is your order. I am a soldier, loyal to you and to the Empire.
自分は　帝国と総統に
忠誠を尽くす軍人です。
ご命令とあらば。
（拍手）
（ゼーリック）彼こそ
ガミラスの輝ける星である。
Hurray to the shining star of Garmillas!
A promotion to High Chief General?
（タラン）上級大将に　昇進か。→
What concerns me is your popularity among the people.
心配なのは　君が　国民の間で→
人気が高いことだ。
Be wary. Many of those who surround His Lordship do not think well of your rise.
（ディッツ）気をつけろ。
総統の取り巻きには→
お前の成功を
快く思っていない者が多い。
Goer, your new direct superior, is one of Sideburns Zoellik's lackeys.
赴任先のゲールは
もみあげゼーリックの腰巾着だぞ。
I'm not interested in politics.
私は　政治には　興味ありません。
（２人）んん…。
バレラスも変わりましたね。
Baleras has changed.
おお～　そういえば
君のところのメルダ嬢ちゃん→
Oh, I was glad to hear your Melda was safe.
無事だったそうで
よかったじゃないか。
ああっ！　あの親不孝者め。
My daughter is very inconsiderate. She refuses to share any details.
詳しい経緯は
何一つ　話そうとしないのだぞ。
まったく…。
見たかね？　エルク。
Do you see that, Elk? Even the fierce Admiral Ditz has a weakness.
猛将ディッツにも
弱点は　あるようだ。
おい　タラン！
Quiet, Talan.
提督に　一つお願いがあります。
I have a request, Admiral.
ん？
例の特務艦を→
Could you lend me that specialized operations ship?
自分に
お貸し願えないでしょうか？
あれをか？
That ship?
（親衛隊員）止まれ！
Halt.
What's wrong?
（ディッツ）どうした？
親衛隊の検問です。
Imperial Guard checkpoint. Your identification.
身分証を。
（親衛隊員）失礼しました。
（タラン）何かあったのかね？
Excuse me.
Has something happened?
（親衛隊員）
洋上プラントで　サボタージュです。
Sabotage at the Floating Plant.
What are those?
（ドメル）あれは？
（親衛隊員）摘発した反乱分子です。
Rebel forces we found.
見たところ　一般市民のようだが。
They look like ordinary citizens.
It doesn't matter.
関係ありません。
ギムレー長官の指示で→
Director Gimleh has ordered that they all be sent to the prison planet.
全員　収容所惑星送りです。→
どうぞ　お通りください。
ガーレ・デスラー！
Please pass through. Ghale Desler!
（ディッツ）ギムレーめ…。
（タラン）君の言うとおりだな。→
Damn that man.
You were right. Baleras has changed.
バレラスは変わったよ。
You want to be let out here?
（タラン）ここでいいのか？
（ドメル）はい。
Yes.
What we discussed earlier... I'll take care of it.
さっきの話な
こちらで手配しておく。
Thank you.
感謝します。
サァーー（雨音）
ゴロゴロゴロ…（雷鳴）
（タラン）いいのか？　あの艦は
総統の裁断がなければ…。
Are you sure? The Leader's permission is required to use that ship.
艦隊運用の責任者は　俺だ。
I am Supreme Commander of Astrofleets.
ふっ　聞かなかったことにしよう。
I'll pretend I never asked.
国家元帥は
版図の拡大を推し進め→
The Imperial Marshal continues to expand our territory,
ジレルの魔女が　それを喧伝する。
and the Jirel witch spreads his propaganda.
副総統は　お飾りなうえ→
The Vice-Commander is a figurehead, the Guard's arrogance is astonishing,
親衛隊の傍若無人は
目を覆うばかり。
and our leader...
そして　総統は…。
遷都を考えておられるらしい。
...plans to move the capital.
（ディッツ）遷都？　帝都をか？
To move the capital? To move Baleras?
大統合だよ。→
A great unification.
我々は　どこから来て→
Where have we come from, and where are we going?
どこへ
向かおうとしているのだろうな。
（ディッツ）難しいことを言うな。
Stop playing the philosopher.
クエッ…　クエェー！
（エリーサ）あなたが　この日を
覚えているとは思わなかった。→
I didn't think you remembered this day.
I'm glad you did.
これは　救いね。
総統命令で　一時　帰国した。
At our Leader's bequest, I've temporarily returned.
（エリーサ）そう。
Oh.
クエェーー
うわ～！
こいつ　ロクロック鳥だ！
Look, it's a rokrhok bird!
クエェー　クエェー！
ほら　こっち来いよ！
Come down here!
（エリーサ）生きていれば
ちょうど　あのくらい。
If they were alive, they'd be that age now.
What did our leader want?
総統のご用事は　なんだったの？
He ordered me to command the Milky Way Theatre's armies.
（ドメル）
銀河方面軍の指揮を命じられた。
ああっ！
この！
Hey!
あっ！
銀河系は遠いわ。
ああ。
The Milky Way is far from here.
Yes.
（エリーサ）とても…　遠い。
So very far...
ああ。
Yes.
（ドメル）ああ…。
It is.
私たちは　遠からず　一つとなる。
Before long, we shall be one.
Stay there and watch, as the wolf I've released catches its prey in its jaws...
（デスラー）
君は　そこで　私の放った狼が→
獲物に
牙を立てるのを見ていたまえ。
Doctor Sado?
佐渡先生？
一命は　取り留めましたが→
They survived, but it appears they suffer from amnesia...
どうも　記憶障害を
起こしているようですね。
（佐渡）
しかし　ひどい事故じゃったな。
What a terrible accident.
テロだってうわさも
あるようです。
Rumors say it was terrorism.
Ms. Yuki Mori
ピッ　ピッ　ピッ　ピッ（心電計の音）
あっ。
（林・鼻歌）
♪♪　ふふふふ～　ふふふふ～ん
Auto-navigation system, all clear.
（林）自動航法装置に異常なしっと。
ピピピピッ…（キーボード操作音）
（林）えっ？
あぁ…。→
あっ…　はっ！　ああっ！
きゃあ～！　うわっ…　あっ。
（真琴）んん～　どうしたの？→
What's wrong? Have a weird dream?
変な夢でも見たのかにゃ？
うん…。
Yeah. Uh, a dream about a beautiful woman!
えっと…　きれいな女の人の夢。
（真琴）きれいだったら→
If she was beautiful, it was a good dream.
いいじゃない。
ダメ！　ダメ　ダメ　ダメ！
No! No, no, no, wait!
待って！　あっ。
はぁ～。
≪（真琴）ええ～　林さんまで？
You, too, Hayashi?
（林）
本当だよ。　きれいな女の人でさ。
Really, it was a beautiful woman.
（真琴）う～ん　自動航法室か。
The auto-navigation room, huh?
（林）それが　似てたんですよ。
（佐渡）過労じゃな。
It looked just like her!
Overwork.
（真琴）でも　開かずの間って
言われてる部屋ですよ。→
But they say that the room's haunted.
I wouldn't be surprised if there were a ghost...
本物が出たって…。
（林）いや　座敷童じゃないから。
It wasn't that kind of ghost.
（真琴）誰が　座敷童やねん！
（林）一糸まとわぬ姿だよ。
How am I supposed to know?!
And she was naked...
（真琴）勝手に脱がすな！
（佐渡）バカやっとらんで→
Don't remove her clothes!
Stop being stupid, drink this, and go to sleep!
これのんで　寝てろ！
（林）ああっ。→
「トランキライザー」？→
Tranquilizer?
森さんに
そっくりだったんだよな…。
She looked just like Mori...
（真琴）うちより
新見さんのとこ行きですかねぇ。
Maybe he should be heading to Niimi instead of us...
≪シューン
先生。
Doctor.
病室の方は　終わりました。
（佐渡）おお～　ご苦労さん。
I've finished cleaning the patient room.
病室の方は　終わりました。
（佐渡）おお～　ご苦労さん。
Oh, good work.
（百合亜）ん？
≫シューン
（星名）山本三尉→
（佐渡）んん…。
≫シューン
（星名）山本三尉→
Ensign Yamamoto, you are now released from the brig.
現時刻をもって　懲罰解除です。→
（佐渡）んん…。
６日のお務め　ご苦労さまでした。
I'm sure it was a rough six days.
（玲）ん？　あっ！
（加藤）もう　バカすんじゃねぇぞ。
Don't do anything else stupid.
We lost a valuable ship...
（玲）大切な機体を１機
失ってしまいました。
Your safety is more important.
（篠原）お前が無事だ
ってのが大切なんだよ。
えっ？
ふっ。　まあ　そういうこった。
Yeah, that's how it is.
あっ。
（ハーモニカの演奏）
≫罰当番は終わったかな～？
You finished your punishment?
Yup, everything's shining.
とっくに。　もうピッカピカ。
また吹いてたんだ。
You were playing that again.
ああ。　こう…　気が紛れるんだ。
Yes, it helps me relax.
Really...
そう…。
ねえ　私も　山本さんみたいに→
Hey, do you think I'd be able to pilot this like Yamamoto does?
かっこよく操縦できるかな？
ダメでしょ。
Nope.
ダメって何よ！
ふっ。
What do you mean, "nope"?
ほんとは気になって　来たんだろ？
You're here because of her, right?
あっ。
≪あいつの気持ちも分かるんだ。
I understand how she feels.
あんな話
俺だって　信じたくないさ。
I don't want to believe it, either.
俺だって　ヤツらの攻撃で→
I lost my family to their attacks, too...
家族は　みんな…。
And my brother died in battle. Never knowing he was just a decoy.
兄さんも戦死した。
自分たちが囮だったとも
知らずにね。
Kodai...
古代君…。
Don't look like that. I've settled things in my mind.
そんな顔するなよ。
えっ？
もう　自分の中で　整理はついた。
Right now, I'll just trust Captain Okita.
今は　沖田艦長を信頼している。
ただ　あいつは　俺と違って→
But he isn't like me. He has family to protect.
守るべき家族が残ってるんだ。
Safe Journeys
In that sense, I'm a little jealous.
そういう意味じゃ
ちょっと羨ましいかな。
You can make a new family.
家族は　新しく作れるよ。
えっ？
Everyone on this ship is your family.
この艦のみんなが家族。
You're right.
そうだな。
（徳川）
お前んとこは　おふくろさんと→
Don't you have a mother and a brother?
弟だったかな？
えっ？
（徳川）うちは　長男夫婦と孫→
My eldest has a wife and child, and then I've another son.
それに　次男が１人。
あぁ…。
（徳川）その次男が　わしのような
船乗りになりたいなんぞと→
My second son says he wants to be a sailor like me.
言いおってなぁ。
A sailor?
船乗りに。
艦なんて　残っちゃおらんのにな。
Not that there are any ships left.
でも　いい話じゃないですか。
But isn't it nice anyway?
うむ…　いや　次男より孫だ。
えっ？
No, I'm more interested in my grandchild.
これが　めっぽうかわいくてな。
She's very cute. I can't die until I find her a good husband.
あれに
いい婿を見つけてやるまでは→
わしは死ねんのだ。
徳川さんの　お眼鏡に適うのは→
Won't be easy to find someone who meets your standards...
大変そうだなぁ。
そうだ！　お前　立候補せんか？
I know! Why don't you marry her?
アイ子は　将来　いい女になるぞ。→
Aiko's going to grow up to be a very beautiful lady.
And you can have her!
お前なら許す！
えっ！　いや　そんな…　えっ？
No, I couldn't...
I'll think about it.
考えさせていただきます。
（２人）ははははっ！
はははっ　ははっ。
なあ　島。
えっ？
Hey, Shima.
Sometimes there's more than one truth. You have your truth, and they have theirs.
真実っちゅうもんは
一つとはかぎらん。
こちらには　こちらの
相手には　相手の真実が→
あるもんだ。
だが　事実は　一つだけだ。→
But there is only one reality. The war really happened.
戦争は起こっちまった。
Even so, you and I have our families.
それでも
わしやお前には　家族がいる。→
わしらは恵まれとる…
そう思わんか？
We are blessed. Don't you think so?
≫コン　コン（ノック）
≫古代進　入ります。
Kodai Susumu, coming in.
失礼します。
こちらで　最後になります。
Excuse me. This is the final room.
うっ！
ちょうどよかった。
Excellent timing. I was just thinking I wanted to talk to you.
お前と
話をしたいと思っていたところだ。
えっ？
ん？　あっ…。
（島）そっか　出てきたんだ。
６日たちましたから。
I see, so you're out.
It's been six days.
なんですか？　それ。
（島）ん？
Why are you holding a mop?
ああ～　君と同じようなもんかな。
Oh, I suppose the same thing that happened to you.
I disobeyed orders, too.
わしも
あのとき　命令違反を犯した。
えっ？
先制攻撃に反対して→
I opposed the surprise attack, and I was removed from duty.
解任された。
そうだったんですか。
Is that what happened?
正しかったと思うか？
思います。
Do you think I was right?
I do.
命令に逆らう…
軍人としては　間違った行動だ。
I disobeyed an order. That isn't what a soldier should do.
あってはならない。
しかし　それは…。
Not ever.
But then...
だが　軍人であっても
一人の人間として→
But there are times even a soldier should act like a human being.
行動しなくてはならんときもある。
人は　間違いを犯す。
People make mistakes.
もし
それが　命令であったとしても→
You need the courage to disobey an order you believe is wrong, to remain true to yourself.
間違っていると思ったら
立ち止まり→
自分を貫く勇気も必要だ。
そう　わしは思う。
That is what I think.
I understand how you feel.
気持ちは分かるよ。
ん？
肉親の敵を取りたかったんだろ？
I believe you wished to avenge your family.
あげく　その敵に助けられました。
And in the end, the enemy saved me.
だとしても　君は　自分の気持ちに
正直に行動したんだ。
Even so, you stayed true to your feelings.
メルダと分かり合えると言った
古代さんは→
Maybe Kodai was too idealistic when he said we and Melda could understand each other.
理想主義に過ぎるかもしれない。
However, I understand a little now.
でも　今は　少し分かる。
（大吾・回想）((父さんは
戦いに行くんじゃない。→
Your father isn't going to fight.
宇宙人とだって
きっと　友達になれるさ))
I'm sure we can be friends with the aliens.
彼女は敵だ。　憎くないのか？
She's our enemy. Don't you hate her?
I don't feel hatred anymore.
憎しみは　もう感じません。
Really?
（島）((本当に？))
((ああ。　希望を持つんだ))
Yes, hold on to hope.
A Message from the Yamato Cafeteria
I had time to cool my head.
（玲）頭を冷やす時間を
頂けましたから。
Limited-Time Special Menu
（島）そうか…。
ポーン（エレベーターの音）
I see.
Milky Way Lunch (only ten served per day)
古代さんが　心配していました。
Kodai was worried.
俺は　上だから。→
I'll be heading up.
玲ちゃん→
Akira... Thank you.
ありがとう。
あぁ～あ！　頭冷やすか。
Guess I'll go cool my own head!
あっ。
How long are they running that limited-time lunch?
例の期間限定ランチ　いつまでだ？
来週まで…　だったかな。
Until next week, I think.
明日なら空いてる。
I'm free tomorrow.
ふっ。
ふふっ。　オーケー。
Okay.
≫ドドーン！
なんだ!?
What?
Hit on our port side! A torpedo!
（太田）
左舷に被弾！　魚雷攻撃です！
Episode 12: What Lies Beyond
The Yamato hides, wounded.
The eyes of a hunter search for it.
The shadow of an invisible enemy, sharpening its fangs.
Is there any way to escape those fangs?
A howl resounds through the emptiness of space.
Next time: The Wolf from Another Dimension.
There are 317 days left before humanity is extinct.
今日は、井上貴博アナウンサーと
一緒にお伝えします。
今日は、６８年前の沖縄戦で
旧日本軍の組織的な戦闘が
終結したとされる日。